原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/KOiEwXF4ZC4
原视频发布日期：20200620
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
你好 我是Scott Manley
Hello, it's Scott Manley here.
几星期前 我谈到了SpaceX已经砍掉的火箭设计
A couple of weeks ago I talked about SpaceX has abandoned rocket designs.
本周 我想谈谈其他技术 也就是SpaceX已经宣传过 然后砍掉的那种
This week I want to talk about other technologies which SpaceX have pitched and then abandoned.
不一定是火箭整体的设计
Concepts that weren't entire vehicle designs
但仍是计划中的东西 可能会被纳入一个完整的运载火箭
but plans for things that might have been incorporated into a full up launch vehicle.
但最终这些计划都没有看到曙光 或者已经被更好的东西所取代
But ultimately never saw the light of day or have been replaced with something better.
当然 SpaceX以其回收助推器(一级火箭)并重复使用的能力而闻名
SpaceX are of course known for their ability to recover their boosters and reuse them.
而虽然我们直到2016年才看到着陆
and while we didn't see a landing until 2016.
这个概念从公司成立之初就一直伴随着他们
The concept has always been with them from the earliest days of the company.
但助推器一开始的计划并不是以那种华丽的悬停猛击动作着陆
But instead of landing the rocket boosters in that magnificent hover slam maneuver,
而是使用降落伞
the original plan was to use parachutes.
第一个提出用降落伞回收火箭级的并不是SpaceX
They weren't the first to suggest recovering rocket stages with parachutes by any means.
即使是早期的红石火箭 也就是那个用来发射第一个水星飞船的火箭
Even the early Redstone rocket used to launch the first Mercury capsules
设计时就在返回舱下面留有放置降落伞的空间
were designed with room for parachutes under the capsule.
但当然 在这之后使用降落伞进行回收就被美国(各种)航天计划放弃了
But of course the parachute recovery has been abandoned by the US space program
直到航天飞机计划出现
until the Space Shuttle program came along
航天飞机回收并翻新了固体火箭助推器
which recovered and refurbished the solid rocket boosters.
那么当SpaceX公司在考虑开发低成本火箭时 重复使用就是他们计划的核心部分
So when SpaceX was looking at developing a low-cost rocket, reuse was a core part of their plans.
而早期的猎鹰1号飞行中 包含了Irvin降落伞公司制造的降落伞
And the early Falcon 1 flights included parachutes built by Irvin Parachute Corporation
该公司还制造了航天飞机助推器回收系统
who also built the Shuttle booster recovery system.
猎鹰1号上的回收伞在级间段内 在第一级的顶部
The recovery parachute on the Falcon 1 was inside the interstage, at the top of the first stage
而实际上它占据的空间会延伸到二级红隼发动机的发动机喷管中
and it would actually extend up inside the engine Bell of the second stage Kestrel engines.
当助推器下降时 其降落伞将在约4公里的高度进行部署
When descending it would deploy as an altitude of about four kilometers
并在理论上让助推器进行在水中的软着陆
and in theory delivered the booster to a soft touchdown and water.
第一次猎鹰1号发射在一二级分离前失败了 所以降落伞没有进行测试
The first Falcon 1 launch failed before the stage separation so the chute wasn't tested.
但第二次发射成功进行了一二级分离
But the second launch did deploy the second stage
在助推器消失在地平线之前 发射场对其进行了追踪
and the booster was tracked from the launch site before it disappeared below the horizon.
回收船在几小时后到达了预定的着陆区
Our recovery ship reached the predicted landing area a few hours later.
但它并没有找到助推器 也没有收到助推器天线发射的任何信号
But it didn't find the booster or receive any pings from its beacons.
第四次猎鹰1号飞行的数据显示 助推器很可能在再入过程中被摧毁
Data from the fourth Falcon 1 flight showed that the booster had probably been destroyed during reentry.
而在有机会部署降落伞之前 助推器需要升级才能在再入过程中存活下来
And they would need upgrades to survive the descent before it had any chance to deploy parachutes.
猎鹰9号的前两次飞行也在级间段加入了降落伞
The first two flights of Falcon 9 also included parachutes in the interstage
但助推器在再入过程中也解体了
but the boosters also broke up during descent
于是这就结束了SpaceX的用降落伞回收助推器的计划
and that was the end of SpaceX s plans to recover boosters with parachutes.
好吧 所以下一个被抛弃的概念 我想谈的是梅林2 这是一个更大的版本的梅林发动机
Okay so next abandoned concept I want to talk about is the Merlin 2 which is a larger version of the Merlin engine.
SpaceX会用单台梅林2号发动机取代猎鹰9号一级的所有9台梅林发动机
And they would replace all nine Merlin engines in the first stage of a Falcon 9 with his single Merlin 2
推力甚至还要再多一些
and it would actually have more thrust on top of that.
那么 发动机的循环和喷注器的设计并没有任何真正的改变
Now there weren't any real changes to the engine cycle or the injector design.
它实际上只是梅林的放大版
It was really just a scaled up version of the Merlin.
一台梅林2号发动机可以产生高达750吨的推力
And a single Merlin 2 engine would develop a thrust of up to 750 tons
这实际上会使它与驱动土星5号的F1发动机非常相似
which would actually make it very similar to the F1 engine that powered the Saturn 5.
所以在2010年的联合推进会议上 梅林2号的设计细节出现在了演讲中
So details of the design of the Merlin 2 came up in a presentation in 2010 at the joint propulsion conference.
而论文的重点虽然是简单地用简化版取代现有的猎鹰9号
and while the paper focused on simply replacing the existing Falcon 9 with a simplified version,
他们也在研究建造更大更好的火箭 以充分利用梅林2号的能力
they also looked at building bigger and better rockets that could exploit the power of the Merlin 2.
于是就有了猎鹰X号 它将推进剂储罐的直径扩大到6米
So there was the Falcon X and this would scale up the propellant tanks to 6 meter diameter
并能安装3台梅林2号发动机 拥有差不多38吨的近地轨道运载能力
and allow 3 Merlin 2 engines with the ability to throw a bit 38 tons into low-earth orbit.
当然还有用3个这样的助推器芯级捆绑而成的猎鹰X重型火箭
And of course there was the Falcon X Heavy made of three of these booster cores bolted together
并可携带高达125吨的有效载荷
and that would carry payloads of up to 125 tons.
但还有一款猎鹰XX
But then there was a Falcon XX.
一枚10米宽的助推器 百米高 配备6台梅林2号发动机 能够将140吨的载荷送入轨道
A 10 meter wide booster, a hundred metres tall with six Merlin two engines and able to throw 140 tons into orbit.
而这样一来 它的体积和近地轨道有效载荷质量就和Starship差不多了
And this would put it in the same ballpark as Starship in terms of size and low Earth orbit payload.
但并没有Starship计划中的完全可重复使用性
but without the full reusability planned for Starship
而这部分原因是梅林2比猛禽效率较低
and this is partly because the Merlin 2 has lower efficiency compared to the Raptors.
实际上猎鹰9号上的9个小发动机是其能够进行助推器降落的重要原因
The thing is having nine small engines on the Falcon 9 is a big part of why is able to perform the booster landings.
当助推器几乎是空的时候 只需要相当于发射时推力的5%这么小的程度就可以悬停了
When the booster is almost empty only needs a bit 5% of its launch thrust to hover
所以能够只使用九个引擎中的一个 是能够控制下降过程的一个巨大优势
and so being able to use just one of the nine engines is a huge advantage in being able to control the descent.
而这一点直到很多年后才被真正意识到
And that wasn't really appreciated until many years later.
所以我们并没有听到更多关于梅林2号的消息
And so we didn't really hear more about the Merlin 2.
而且它消失了 与此同时猛禽成为了SpaceX的下一代发动机
Instead it disappeared and Raptor became SpaceX's next generation engine,
与梅林2相比 猛禽是一款更为复杂的设备
a much more complicated device compared to the Merlin 2.
猛禽展现了它的多功能性
（作为一个圣诞树的功能）
但其实猛禽早于梅林2 在2009年就出现了
But the Raptor actually appeared before the Merlin 2 in 2009.
不过当时它是一款闭式循环氢氧发动机
Back then however it was a closed cycle hydrogen-oxygen engine
作为猎鹰9号的二级发动机
that was being pitched as a second stage engine for the Falcon 9.
其推力可与梅林媲美 但很明显 其比冲比梅林号高很多
And it would have a thrust comparable to the Merlin but obviously a specific impulse was much much higher.
但这一概念 当然 在2012年被放弃
But that concept, of course was abandoned in 2012.
猛禽目前的形式是燃烧甲烷的高推力一级发动机
The Raptor for current form as a high thrust first stage engine burning methane
并采用全流量分级燃烧循环
and using a full flow staged combustion cycle.
那么 在这些年里 它的尺寸 推力和性能都发生了一些变化
Now it's changed a bit over the years in terms of size thrust and performance
但目前是SpaceX公司未来的发动机 而且是可以追溯到2012年的型号
but is currently the future engine of SpaceX and it dates back to the 2012 model.
但猛禽发动机有一个被放弃的概念
But there is one abandoned concept for the Raptor engine.
2016年 美国空军授予SpaceX公司一份开发猛禽的合同
In 2016 the US Air Force awarded SpaceX a contract to develop Raptor
让其作为猎鹰9号更高效的二级发动机 取代目前的二级发动机
as a higher efficiency second stage engine for the Falcon 9 replacing the current second stage
而这将有助于一些任务概况的制定
and this would help with some mission profiles.
而SpaceX公司已经研究并利用这一点来开发猛禽 并进行了纸面的提案
And while SpaceX has worked on and used that to develop the Raptor and come up with proposals on paper,
但这个概念还没有被开发成一个实际工作的上面级
the concept hasn't been developed into an actual working upper stage.
好了 不说发动机了
Okay so enough about the engines.
当载人龙飞船首次亮相时
Back when Crew Dragon was first revealed.
SpaceX希望它能在着陆点进行精确的反推式着陆
SpaceX wanted it to perform a precision propulsive touchdown at a landing site
使用超级天龙座推进器 而不是使用降落伞和海上溅落
using the Super Draco thrusters instead of using parachutes and a splashdown.
当然也有很多人怀疑这是否能通过NASA的风险规避型安全审查
And there were certainly many who were skeptical this would ever make it past NASA's risk-averse safety reviews.
不过 SpaceX有着充分的技术理由来调查反推式着陆
But there were good technical reasons to investigate the propulsive landing.
与其他载人航天器不同的是
Unlike other human-rated spacecraft,
载人龙飞船的超级天龙座发射逃逸发动机是内置在飞船里的
Crew Dragons Super Draco launch escape thrusters are built into the capsule.
逃逸所使用的推进剂
The propellant supply needed for it for the abort is the same
与在太空中操纵的较小的天龙座发动机所使用的燃料是相同的
which is also used for the smaller Draco thrusters used for maneuvering in space.
这些设备 用于火箭发射失败时的逃逸的同时
The same hardware that is needed to push the capsule free from a fallen rocket
也需要用来将飞船着陆在着陆场上
has the ability to bring the capsule stop at a landing pad
在逃逸时 (因为逃逸会消耗反推式着陆时的燃料 所以)不管怎样还是需要降落伞
and parachutes are required either way for the abort scenario
所以如果在反推式着陆过程中出现问题 也可以使用降落伞
so those would be available if there was a problem during a propulsive landing.
现在飞船需要一些额外的硬件
Now the capsule would need some extra hardware.
它需要一些用于控制着陆的传感器
It would need some sensors for controlling the touchdown
当然 它也需要一套起落架
and of course it would need a set of landing legs
在视觉上 它将穿过隔热板
which in the visualizations would extend through the heat shield.
当然 任何侵入隔热板的行为 都会让NASA的安全人员有点紧张
And of course any intrusion through the heat shield does make the safety people at NASA a little edgy
但事实是 并不是安全问题终结了这个概念
but the truth is it wasn't safety concerns that really killed this as a concept.
而是时间 时间是最重要的资源
It was more the time was the most important resource.
无论如何 他们都需要有一个降落伞
They needed to have a parachute either way.
而这是一个很容易的争论 那就是SpaceX可以放弃反推式着陆 而只是使用降落伞
And it was an easy argument that they could drop propulsive landing and just use those parachutes
甚至降落伞的部署
and even the parachute deployment
也是载人龙飞船研发过程中比较麻烦的一件事
was one of the more troubling things during the development of Crew Dragon.
SpaceX刚在2019年年底(才)公开记录其降落伞测试的成功率
SpaceX were publicly documenting its success rate of the parachute test just at the end of 2019
所以反推式着陆技术也是红龙飞船概念的核心
So the propulsive landing technology was also core to the concept of Red Dragon.
这是SpaceX提出的火星任务
SpaceX proposed a Mars mission
也就是运送一个实验性的有效载荷到火星上 以及一个改装过的龙飞船
where an experimental payload would be transported to Mars and a modified Dragon capsule.
红龙飞船将用重型猎鹰发射到火星转移轨道上
The Red Dragon would be launched onto the Mars transfer trajectory on a Falcon Heavy.
而着陆将主要依赖红龙飞船
And landing would be heavily dependent on Dragon
通过其空气动力学(特性)来尽可能地减少速度
using his aerodynamics to bleed off as much speed as possible
同时保持升力 然后用超级天龙座进行降落
while maintaining lift and then performing the landing using with Super Dracos.
与其他火星航天器不同的是 降落过程中不会涉及降落伞
Unlike other Martian spacecraft, no parachutes would have been involved in the landing process.
红龙飞船最初是在2011年作为可能的低成本NASA发现任务提出的
Red Dragon was originally proposed as a potential low cost NASA discovery mission in 2011.
该提议包括一个钻探实验
The proposal included a drilling experiment
和一个可以进行提取水和生产推进剂的实验
and an experiment which would perform water extraction and propellant production.
然而它未能获得该计划的进一步资助
However it failed to get further funding from the program.
但SpaceX继续开发这个概念
But SpaceX continued to develop the concept
直到2017年 马一龙宣布停止该项目 改用Starship
until 2017 when Elon announced that the project was being discontinued in favor of Starship.
当然 虽然当时还不叫Starship
Although at the time of course it wasn't known as Starship.
它被称为ITS或BFR
It was known as the ITS or the BFR.
但无论如何 我认为今天这期节目最好到此为止
But either way I think this is a good place to leave off.
我们还有一整集的废弃项目要谈
We have a whole other episode of abandoned projects to talk about.
在那之前 我是Scott Manley
Until then I'm Scott Manley.
切记 注意飞行安全
Fly safe.